do
[Music]
so
hello everybody good day good evening
and welcome to the latest episode of the
ask a budget show where you ask me the
questions and i answer your questions
so before we begin let me greet all of
you first of all wishing you all a very
happy rama navami
and i can see nihal tamagna prathana
the oldie
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you wherever you are
in the world
and let's get right into it let's get
into the questions as always what you've
asked lots of questions i have picked a
bunch of these and let's see how many i
can answer today i'll try and answer as
many as possible
so let us begin with question number one
what is question number one
this is by alex
you speak a lot about western colonial
acts against the eastern world world and
its indigenous peoples that's fair
westerners live in plundered wealth and
land from other civilizations however
most westerners today have done no such
colonizing i a 21 year old american
acknowledge that i live in wealth that
was unfairly taken
but i personally didn't know such
atrocities and neither have my peers or
parents we were born into this
there is a movement in the west saying
that we should live in sorrow and guilt
our whole lives what do you personally
think is a just way to live
knowing all this about our western
history
what realistic fair reparations would
you like to see
i am sure a lot of interested and
curious westerners who have been
following your account would like to
hear your opinion on this
it's a very good question so uh
yeah it is obviously true that the west
whatever wealth and prosperity they have
it is unfortunately because of the past
five centuries of colonization and
plunder of wealth from
the east mainly india and also from
africa resources and things like that
so that is a fact and i'm glad that some
people realize this
now obviously you are 100 correct you
have done no such colonizing your
parents your peers the people who live
in the west today have done no such
thing and therefore i disagree with
people who say that the people of west
should live
in this permanent state of guilt and
what does it say guilt and sorrow your
whole lives no it's not your fault that
what it's not your fault what your
ancestors did i don't believe in
in transferring guilt from generation to
generation especially when the newest
latest generation has done no such thing
so first of all
as long as you realize where the wealth
came from and you acknowledge the fact
that it's been stolen i don't see any
reason for you to live in guilt for what
several generations ago your
ancestors did now what is also true is
that even today there is there are
multiple numerous forms of
neocolonization that are still going on
for instance africa is still being
plundered actively whether it is by
european powers or by
by by the us
the us is still a hegemonic power that
dictates to the world what the world
should do so these activities are
happening right now in our lifetime and
in in some way or the other
that government that does it represents
you it is in a way whether you like it
or not
your will that is being acted out
through your government because the us
is like they say a democracy it's a
two-party state which which is not quite
a democracy in my opinion but let it be
that way
so the thing is this uh
you you are asking is is uh
what realistic fair reparations would i
would like to see i don't expect any
reparations it's not possible for the
western powers to give out reparations
and whatever reparations even if they
are willing to give out will not be
sufficient to cover what's happened i
mean the kind of wealth
historians and economists have
calculated the amount of wealth that uh
that the british
uh took out of india over over two or
three centuries and the amount the
figure they reached was approximately 45
trillion dollars in today's money
approximately maybe 45 or 50. now is
there any way any the uk can pay that
sort of money back to india it's simply
impossible and then even if it is paid
to india
how will they do it because that's like
three times what is the current uk gdp
per year
must be around three four trillion uh
billion dollars yeah
per year
maybe trillion
so
to pay 15 times that is not feasible at
all it's not practical it's impossible
and nobody will accept will agree to do
that so it's not it is unrealistic to
expect any reparations from the west to
the east or to africa it's not going to
happen the only thing that needs to
happen is that all the
neo-colonial activities that are still
happening whether it is interference in
the internal affairs of india by the
united states and other western powers
whether it is the continuing plunder of
wealth and resources from africa which
is still ongoing i mean what the west
does is it
installs these puppet
regimes in africa africa is a broken
continent full of straight lines that
don't reflect the history
of the african people there are so many
different cultures in africa and they've
been divided by by the straight lines
let me show you an example what do i
mean by that
uh let me share the map let's take a
look at what africa looks like
google maps here we are so this is
okay let's go to africa you will see the
continent divided by these straight
lines that have been arbitrarily drawn
by western powers
who left the the continent but wanted to
continue their influence there so what
you do is you create nation states that
don't respect or recognize
uh ethnic boundaries
the the the places where ethnic groups
have traditionally lived so you have you
create these nations where you have
multiple ethnic groups
that are divided across boundaries and
then they are in conflict because they
see their ethnic identity as being
above the national identity because the
nation the nation that they live in is
an artificially created nation they
are not
culturally and historically tied to
those boundaries
and then what these nations do is that
they impose these puppet dictatorial
regimes in africa that's the history of
africa for the past century
full of civil war full of dictators
petty dictators thin pot dictators
whether it is in zimbabwe
angola wherever
drc mali
all over africa you have these petty
dictators these corrupt dictators
so by installing these petty corrupt
dictators what the west does
is that it continues its colonial
activities in africa so if you have a
corrupt dictator who owes his
uh power to you to an european power
or a western power then that person will
do everything to keep that relationship
going which means they will allow you to
keep on plundering their wealth for gold
for cobalt for uranium for whatever else
is available lithium whatever your land
is rich in you're gonna keep allowing
the western powers to do that
so these are things that need to stop
and these are all being done even today
by the west even even the chinese are
now
getting into the fray for the past one
and a half decades they have been
investing a lot in africa and they are
continuing similar policies
so my point is very simple it is unfair
to expect today's
people who live in the west
to bear the guilt of what their
ancestors did several generations ago
i do not see the people of the west
today as being guilty
of what their ancestors is of course
some of them have this attitude that
what our ancestors did was right it was
justified because we did it because we
can and we are proud of it so the these
attitudes are very problematic and
that's why there is this
deep bitter divide between the east and
the west people in india today are sick
and tired of being lectured by the west
it's still happening all the time on
social media you can see it in real time
you go on twitter or wherever else you
have the us government lecturing india
about democracy a two-party state is
lecturing india a vibrant democracy
about what democracy should be like it's
a joke a two-party state is just one
rung above above a one-party state the
us is a two-party state and they want to
come and talk to us about democracy so
this lecturing needs to stop it's not
gonna stop until india raises its
profile and becomes a major power or in
its own right that's the only thing
india has to do so i expect no
reparations i think it's
unrealistic and
impractical to expect any form of
reparations whatever wealth was
plundered from india
in the past three centuries eventually
if india rises and becomes powerful
enough india will be able to reacquire
it through a variety of means
that's how it's going to be whether we
like it or not it's not going to happen
tomorrow next week next month it's going
to happen if india rises properly the
way it should then it's going to happen
over the next century or two centuries
india
may
quite possibly reacquire all that wealth
through a variety of means
so i would say that i
i hold i personally hold no bitterness
towards the people of the west what
their ancestors did it is not your
response what your ancestors did it's
not your fault it's not your
responsibility yes you are enjoying the
fruits of the store and wealth well
that's just how it works in history
that's just how it works that's the
nature of power
so that's
in brief what i have to say about this
okay this is by gita
yes it is always easy to blame others
for one's misfortune but here are some
historical facts
india whose actual name was bharat wash
used to be the greatest nation on earth
for thousands of years
isn't it true they brought about their
own demise didn't they engage in a
colossal civil war that completely
destroyed itself all of it under the
watchful eye of lord krishna himself
any historical or geopolitical
presentation or analysis is utterly and
completely irrelevant and useless
if it is not grounded and based on
morality i can't stress that enough okay
i i get the feeling that this this
person gita is
most likely somebody who lives in the
west and
who may have some kind of affinity for
india or indian culture or something
because the name is gita somebody who in
some way likes india okay i get it the
thing is this
so you are saying that india brought
about brought about its own demise
through this colossal civil war
mahabharata
now when did the mahabharata happen we
don't quite know when it happened it's
clearly something that happened
thousands of years ago
so it is clearly something that happened
that preceded the the mauryan era the
kusan era the gupta era the iran all
that now wasn't india the most
prosperous and most most advanced nation
in the world during the gupta era during
the chola era during the kusan era
during the mauryan era and even during
the sapta sindhu phase of india's
civilization the saraswati phase the
so-called harappan phase right india was
way way more advanced than any other
place in the world
completely fully
industrialized and urbanized
civilization that whose geographical
extent dwarfed egypt plus mesopotamia
plus the middle east put together
so this phase of india's civilization
the the harappan phase the so-called
urban phase is
something that came after the events of
the mahabharata
so
is
the mahabharata something that destroyed
india that's what you're claiming which
is completely untrue
right
and now let's talk about the mahabharata
this colossal civil war that destroyed
india how did it destroy india
in what way did it destroy india let's
understand what this conflict was about
it was
not a civil war
it was a conflict within a family
the kora was in the the pandavas
were cousins it was a single extended
family you could call it a clan
and they had this power struggle
an internal power struggle they both
wanted primacy they want
the kawarawas wanted to rule india and
so did the pandavas and there was this
conflict
that's what this
uh war was about and this war took place
over a number of days in one location in
northern india the battlefield of
kurukshetra which still exists we know
where it is
so the battle the war was localized
confined to one battlefield that was how
it was done it was not spread across all
of india not a single small not a single
city town village was
damaged or destroyed in this
conflict
not a single non-combatant was harmed
not a single civilian was harmed or
killed in this conflict so what are you
talking about
you may have read something about indian
history and this is not something that
only applies to people who are not
indian this applies to indians as well
they have all kinds of misconceptions
about this this conflict
it was fought under a set of rules that
you're gonna fight within this
battlefield and you're not gonna destroy
the country not a single town city or
village was damaged or destroyed not a
single non-combatant was harmed read the
texts
that's where we get the information from
nothing of that sort happened
two sets of warriors two armies fought
each other over a number of days and at
the end
of the conflict the winners were the
pandavas that's what happened now you
speak about geopolitics and history has
to be grounded in morality
geopolitics is about power right or
wrong has nothing to do with geopolitics
ethics and morality have nothing to do
with geopolitics look at the history of
the planet look at the history of the
human species it's a history of conflict
you see morality in conflict what's
happening in yemen right now where is
the morality in what the u.s is doing in
yemen
what is the morality in what the u.s did
in abu ghraib in iraq
two million
iraqi civilians
innocent iraqi men women and children
were killed in iraq
because of the us invasion the second
so-called gulf war where is the morality
in that i don't see you criticizing that
morality but i as an indian
have to be based and grounded in
morality let me explain morality
lord krishna understood this morality
and so did vishnu
the highest morality for a king is that
his
nation and its people should prosper
that is it you must win
non-negotiable
whatever endeavors or conflicts your
nation is engaged in the highest
morality for the king or the ruler or
the emperor or the queen or whoever it
is in charge the highest morality is
that you must succeed and your nation
and your people must prosper in the long
run that is it and lord krishna acted
according to this so did vishnu chanakya
so what happened
in the mahabharata war there was a
terrible war
both sides did i mean not both sides
both sides broke the rules at various
levels
a certain side the the korah was engaged
in certain atrocious activities
right
at the end of the day the kora was lost
the pandavas won they were victorious
and then what did lord krishna do
he asked the pandavas the victorious
pandavas to go to the himalayas and
never come back
that's what he told them to do and
that's and they obeyed him why is that
why did he ask the victorious side to
give up everything and leave
and what he did is that he installed
pariksit the grandson
of arjun the son of
abhimanyo as the king
so the the lineage continued the family
was not destroyed but a new king was put
in place pariksit not yudhisthira not
arjuna not beam none of these people why
is that
let me explain why none of them was
worthy of ruling the country
they had all shown that they were
unworthy of ruling the country
yudhisthira they call him dharmaraj
the guy could not
control his compulsive gambling he
gambled away his kingdom
he gambled away his family his brothers
he gambled away his wife
is a person who does that worthy of ever
being a king no
what about arjun the great warrior the
great survey brave mahan yoda what about
him he had trained his whole life
for war
and when it comes to fighting the war he
developed cold feet and lord krishna was
forced to give a lengthy pravachan on
the battlefield before arjuna was
willing to fight
is a man who has such qualities worthy
of being a king no and so on and so
forth so lord krishna did what is best
for the country for the civilization he
got rid of these he made sure first of
all that the evil side the side that
represented adarma the kauravas were
destroyed he made sure of that through
the pandavas and then he got rid of the
pandavas themselves because they too
were not fit enough or were they enough
to rule
the great civilization and therefore
what happened is that through these
actions
through this war and then the subsequent
permanent exile of the pandavas lord
krishna ensured that this family this
problematic family
was no longer in the picture but he did
not destroy the lineage he installed
parikshith as the king
and parikshit's lineage continued so
that was the right thing to do so this
great colossal civil war it did not
destroy india's civilization it
rejuvenated indian civilization that is
the great feat that lord krishna
achieved and that was the right thing he
he was able to ensure that he followed
the highest morality as a king he was
the king in the west his capital city
was dwarka which we have rediscovered in
the 1980s so
he was the king in the west but he was
the greatest statesman of that era maybe
the greatest statesman india has ever
seen among the top 203 ever and that's
why we still remember him so the thing
is he
acted based on morality and the highest
morality for a king
is to ensure that you your
kingdom your people they have long term
prosperity that's what they achieved so
that's what i would like to see to say
to you gita
you may have read something about india
something about the mahabharat it's not
enough
you have to be born into this culture to
understand and lots of people who are
born in india into this culture they
still don't understand this so
that's what i have to say based on a
little bit of reading you can't you
can't start drawing conclusions about
what is right and what is wrong with
what is morality please please it takes
a lifetime of study study to understand
a little bit of this that's how
complex indian culture is
okay let's take
another question that is most likely
related to this and this is uh by
someone from india vignesh says lord
krishna belongs to the entire world not
only to bharat he is a god not a leader
so i had said in my in one of my answers
on leadership
that lord krishna made this promise when
he said
and so on he made a promise to the
people of india that whenever in the
future there is an existential crisis an
existential conflict to india to the
people of bharath in the land of bharat
and when dharma rises to beyond a
certain extent he will return and
destroy dharma that's what i had said so
this gentleman vignesh is saying that
lord krishna doesn't belong to the
entire it doesn't belong to only india
he belongs to the entire world he's a
god not a leader
what are you smoking sir
he was a living human being he's a
historical figure
and we know that because we have
rediscovered his lost capital city of
dwarka which
the mahabharata says
went under the ocean because of a
colossal earthquake and we have
discovered it exactly where this ancient
text said it would be so he is a
historical figure his capital city has
been rediscovered he was not
he was not some supernatural
mythological mythical figure he was a
living breathing human being one of the
greatest indians one of the greatest
humans ever born he was a leader
he orchestrated the events
that took place during his lifetime he
directed the course of the mahabharata
war and he brought out the best possible
result for india
and he belongs to the people of india he
made this promise to the people of
bharat now some geniuses are saying that
bharat means arjun
please please
don't do this nonsense over here
so lord krishna belonged to the people
of bharat to the to the geographical
area the region the sacred geography of
bharat india and he made this promise to
the people of bharat
and
some people say some so-called spiritual
lyricists they say that i don't serve
any particular group of people i serve
humanity
that's what some people say all of these
spiritual leaders and gurus
many of them say this that i don't serve
india only i serve humanity and all that
let me explain something very clearly
you may claim
to serve humanity but how what
percentage of humanity accepts you as a
leader or a guru you can actually serve
only those people right you may claim to
serve everybody but if only three
percent of the of humanity accepts you
as a leader or a guru then you can
actually serve only three percent of
those people no matter what grandiose
claims you're making i may claim i i
serve the planet of
some other solar system as well but they
don't know me
you can only serve those who accept you
as a leader or a guru
and now tell me something you go to the
middle east will people accept lord
krishna as their leader or the guru or
their
god
you go to the to europe or the order of
the us
what percentage of people will accept
lord krishna as their
as their leader or their guru or their
god or whatever you want to call it
only those
who accept lord krishna
as a god as a guide or whatever only
those
are the people who who he can actually
serve
so he serves the people of bharat those
in bharat who actually
worship him recognize him
believe in him and he serves the sacred
geography of bharat wash which is
a constant that geography may have
certain
other
nation states within but it still
doesn't matter so he served the sacred
geography of bharat wash he served the
people of bharath and he served those
who
are on the side of dharma so that is the
subset of humanity that he served
he belongs only to those people not to
the whole world please disabuse yourself
of these ridiculous notions sir
okay divyrabadi says what no sorry how
was the relationship between the six and
the marathas and why is it that the two
empires
intercept at the northern part of india
this is a good question let's take a
look at the map of the maratha empire
so we know what the maratha empire
looked like let me google it up quickly
and let me share that
so
i just googled the marathon as you can
see
this is the high tide of the maratha
empire they had essentially
reclaimed much of india and liberated
much of india from turkic
occupation and oppression all the way up
to
the southern part of afghanistan
so the and it included punjab
now please remember this the maratha
empire predates the sikh kingdom i do
not consider the six the sikh dominion
to be an empire it is not an empire it's
a tiny little kingdom because let me let
me show you why
let's let they call it the historians
call it the sikh empire in in what sense
or form is it an empire
let us see the size of the sick empire
shall we so-called sick empire
see how small it is in what sense is
this an empire it's just a kingdom an
empire is something that is much larger
than that for instance i could i could
build bring out something else how about
the
vacations
dynasty
the wakatakas are not considered to be
an empire they are considered to be a
kingdom and a dynasty they are actually
larger than the sick empire the
so-called sikh empire and therefore what
i would say is that the sikh
uh
period when they were ruling that small
part of northern india it's not an
imperial era it's not an empire it's
just a kingdom
and the high tide of the sikh kingdom
was under maharaja ranjit singh and he
was a great man he did many good things
etc what's the relationship between the
six and the marathas the sikh kingdom
came after the demise of the decline
eventual slow decline of the maratha
empire
and the sikh kingdom would never have
happened
had the marathas not liberated
that part of india and the rest of india
from the turks
so what the marathas did was they
re-established hinduism
over large parts of india they liberated
india from the turkic occupation and
oppression and because of all of those
things the sikhs were eventually able to
create their own kingdom not empire so
that in very brief and at a very big
picture level high level i can tell you
about
the relationship very tangentially
between the sikhs and the marathas
okay swarup says a remarkable paper
about india has come out today from the
imf its findings are mind-blowing among
them extreme poverty 1.9 dollars per
person per day was below 1 in india in
2019 and 2020 pandemic here in india a
low percentage in extreme poverty for
two consecutive years is considered to
be the elimination of extreme poverty
it's showcasing india's success in pres
particularly for the present
dispensation so are these mind-blowing
findings the reason many are avoiding it
all together
good
very good question have you seen anyone
in the media
in your popular in your in your favorite
media channel news channel or your
whoever else
have you seen anyone speak about this
and these findings these statistics this
data
it comes from the imf
it doesn't come from the indian
government
so the imf
the international monetary fund itself
is showing
that between 2019 and 20-20 which is the
latest data that we have
these two years
extreme poverty which is defined as less
than 1.9 dollars per person per day
extreme poverty was less than one
percent of in the population of india
and that is by definition
the uh elimination
of extreme poverty as per the definition
of the imf and economists worldwide
so even during the pandemic year
the government of india was able to
eliminate extreme poverty we still have
poverty in india there are people below
the poverty line but extreme poverty is
something that's critical
it causes incredible hardship to people
so that has been eliminated in india
and why is no one speaking about this
about this great achievement because it
is mr narendra modi who is in power and
they don't like him and it's the bjp
that's in power and they don't like the
bjp and therefore even though this
government and this prime minister have
achieved this incredible feat for the
first time in the past in the night post
1947 history of india no one wants to
talk about it how shameful is that
we should be proud of the fact that mr
modi has been able to achieve this
through his government and through all
the other people who have put in so much
hard work since 2014
so much change has been brought about
but we don't want to speak about this it
is shameful
that that the media
which is supposed to be this impartial
fair objective
organization or
or institution it is so biased
it doesn't want people in india to know
about what or the good that's that the
government is doing and it's still doing
it's an ongoing process
so yes
if it was somebody else in power they
would have done it but if it was
somebody else in power such a thing
would never have happened
so i would like to personally
congratulate mr modi and the government
of india the current government of india
for this incredible achievement it is
the first time since 1947 that this has
been achieved and i give the credit only
to mr modi and only to the bjp
government nobody else
because india was far from this
situation in 2014 it's because of their
hard work put in year after year that we
have been able to achieve this whether
it is the electrification of the country
whether it is the building of so many uh
toilets whether it is the uh giving
giving everybody in india access to a
bank account or this new achievement all
of this has been done by mr modi and his
government only and the credit goes only
to them and to nobody else so that's
what i would like to put on the record
okay someone says socialism destroyed
venezuela absolutely
100 incorrect
yes venezuela is a socialist country but
you know what destroyed venezuela
look at the graph of the venezuelan
economy look at when the hyperinflation
starts look at when the gdp drops look
at when the poverty begins when what
does it coincide with
socialism was always there
so what precipitated the destruction of
venezuela
let me tell you
u.s sanctions
it is not socialism that destroyed
venezuela it is american sanctions that
destroyed venezuela
vietnam is a socialist country it's
doing really well
china is a socialist country it is a
state-controlled economy
it's not that laissez-faire capitalism
model
it doesn't have a completely free market
so it is not socialism i'm not a
proponent of socialism i'm not i'm not a
fan of socialism but let's be fair
it is not socialism that destroyed
venezuela it is the united states that
deliberately destroyed venezuela end of
story
okay alphabet says why are there many
gujaratis in tanzania zanzibar and other
nearby places okay good question let's
take a look at the map and see where
these places are
where is the map let's bring in the map
right
so let's take a look at the map
so you know where india is
and if you go east of india you come
across the eastern coast of africa
so this here if you can see my mouse
pointer this here is tanzania
zanzibar is
yeah
this little island here
and we also have kenya somalia
mozambique madagascar and other places
eastern africa so gujaratis you will
find them across tanzania across kenya
and
more or less across eastern africa you
will also see some presence of gujaratis
and indians
in madagascar
and so on so
india like i've said before has always
been
a seafaring maritime civilization
you will find presence of indians
very ancient records evidence
of the presence of india of indians in
australia five thousand years before
today you will find
that indian genetics made an entry into
the
australian
gene
pool uh you will find ancient evidence
of indians in africa as well for
instance the first in progression of
indian zebu cattle in africa happened
about 10 000 years ago
and these cattle they don't go for a
walk or for a migration on their own on
their own these are domestic animals
they go when human beings take them
somewhere
so which tells you that 10 000 years
before today indians went to africa with
zebu cattle so it's not some brief
voyage they went with cattle with herds
of cattle to africa indians ancient
indians
and once again about 4 000 is before
today you will find evidence of uh
of carvings or paintings of indian zebu
cattle in ancient egypt
and so so there were at least two waves
of migration of indian cattle into
africa one is about 10 000 years ago one
is about 4 000 years before today
and indians have been if even if you
look at the
people of somalia
of
ethiopia
of sudan etc you will find some indian
characteristics in indian culture there
the kind of dressing style they have
their facial features and appearance
then you will see that same thing all
across the eastern coast of africa
so it looks like indians have been
going to africa for thousands of years
now africa has always been in turmoil
for the past hundred plus years and
therefore nobody has done a proper
genetic survey of the people of the
populations of the p of the humans in
africa once that is done everything will
be clarified when the indian genetics
entered africa
so that is still something that will
happen in the future but it is well
known that indians whether it is from
southern india for kerala or from
gujarat they have been traveling to
africa and living in africa for
centuries on end mostly gujaratis
gujaratis are somehow entrepreneurial
people and you will find the textiles
that you see in gujarat the textile
patterns and the styles that you see in
gujarat you will find the same thing in
places like mozambique in tanzania in
kenya ladies or they are also wear
similar clothes with the same patterns
and you will find indian
influences deep indian influences in the
cuisine
of the countries in eastern africa and
so on so it why are there so many
gujaratis there because i think the
gujaratis have traditionally been
traveling people and entrepreneurial
people and they put down deep roots in
africa that go back centuries if not
thousands of years and it is well known
that when this individual
vasco de gama
came was searching for india he found an
indian sailor somewhere as indian
merchant or traveler somewhere in
eastern africa and that's how he was
able to reach india from there
so i'm not sure if that person was
gujarati or was from kerala but he
reached
calicut
and that's how the
the next cycle of uh invasions started
so that's the story of indians and in
specific to be more specific gujaratis
in eastern africa it's a very ancient
story it it begins before gujarat or
maharashtra or all of these places where
even a thing it's way before that
indians have been going to africa for
about 10 000 years at least
radio says what are your thoughts on the
introduction of african cheetahs in
india
is it not a bad idea
to give
precious funding to a foreign species
i think it's far better to utilize these
resources in the conservation of local
species such as sloth bears indian
wolves civet cats striped hyenas and
local species of various other animals
like small wild cats
the caracal for instance and so on even
some part of this budget can also be
used for the conservation of himalayan
himalayan brown bears
we need to
spend sufficient money to conserve the
species that we still have the tiger the
lion and various other small obscure
species various snakes serpents pythons
hedgehogs porcupines all kinds of
species we have it's a very rich
uh ecosystem that we have in various
parts of india it's all interconnected
we have the brown himalayan red panda
the small one which you find in the
himalayan region we have the
clouded leopard the spotted leopard very
hard to find species in northern india
and so many other interesting species
the golden langur for instance very
interesting language the typical langur
is white with the black face the golden
langur is a golden fur and a black face
very intelligent animals
and so on so what needs to happen is
that all of these species need to be
safeguarded they their habitats must be
safeguarded and preserved
so india needs to do that i think about
10 of india overall is forested that's
how much is left we need to make sure
that it is not destroyed
when it comes to the cheetahs we should
not introduce the african cheetah into
india firstly and why am i saying this
india was the home of the cheetah we had
tens of thousands of cheetahs in india
just three or four hundred years ago
the the
the turk jahangir
or salim
he
had a menagerie of 5000 pet cheetahs
just one guy
right so the cheetah the chitraka was
always part of the indian
wildlife ecosystem it is the british
who
rendered the cheetah extinct by putting
a price on the head of the cheetah
so if you bring back a tail or a head of
the cheetah or even the skin of the you
give it to the local district collector
who collects things then the collector
would actually give you some money for
that
so everybody suddenly looked upon this
as a great gold rush and that's why the
cheetah was hunted into extermination
and the puppet maharajas of india were
also involved in this
right the various puppet maharajas that
were put in place after night after
1857. so that's why the cheetah was
rendered extinct by the foreign
colonizers of india but the british
now the african cheetah
is a different species from the extinct
indian cheetah
and the problem with these african wild
cats is that they they have this virus
the
f i v
virus
feline
immunodeficiency virus that indian
wildcats don't have
we don't want to introduce that african
virus into the indian ecosystem
you must have heard of hiv human
immunodeficiency virus hiv which causes
that this is called aids
there is a simian immunodeficiency virus
siv that infects various monkeys in
africa
and there is a feline immunodeficiency
virus which does the same thing in cats
in various species of cats large cats
small cats all of that lions
in africa and even leopards and all that
so we don't want
that virus to enter the indian ecosystem
we don't want that if you bring african
cheetahs into india
that virus will come into india and from
there it may infect other indian species
of wild cats we don't want that to get
into the tiger and all that because our
animals our cats don't have the natural
immunity to this virus that the african
cats have developed over hundreds of
generations
therefore we must not introduce the
african cheetah into india very clear
but we do want to revive the indian
cheetah which is extinct so what do we
do
well
the indian cheetah is essentially the
asian cheetah and there is still a
population of asiatic cheetahs in our
neighboring country iran
we know there is the small temporary
nation between us but that's a matter of
time so we have a population
of what is essentially nothing but the
indian cheetah still
alive still extent
in iran
so what we should do
is to reintroduce some of those
iranian cheetahs into india with the
cooperation of our iranian friends
right so i have heard about this
proposal since i mean i think this
proposal has been around for decades
from the 1980s onwards people have been
talking about this discussing it but
it's never
fructified
so i think the indian government should
sit down with our parsi cousins
talk to them
request them to send a few cheetahs
a small percentage of their population
to us and we can give something back in
return if they want no problem give and
take
and that is how one could reintroduce
the cheetah into india
it is something that's been part of our
culture and civilization for
10 thousand plus years ever since we
have been our ancestors have lived in
india we have co-existed with the
cheetah and the lion and the tiger so
the lion is now confined to one small
part of india to the gear forest in
saurashtra some gujarat in
peninsula of western india
and we had no longer the cheetah so we
need to ensure that we safeguard these
iconic
felines of india the tiger the lion and
we need to reintroduce
so the way to do it is not to bring it
from africa the cheetah but to
introduce it
via iran from the iranian population
that way the virus won't be introduced
into india
okay this is a
very long question uh by swaroop i read
an article that was recently published
in peer-reviewed journal whatever by the
university of oxford
archaeometry it was about the technology
arabs used to to craft the famous
damascus swords
the technology may have existed in india
before these weapons were built in the
capital city of syria and so on and so
forth a long question i get the point
you're talking about damascus steel what
is known as damascus steel well let me
explain something to you my dear friends
the damascus steel was imported into
syria from india
and in damascus they used that steel
that came in from india to craft those
swords that are known as damascus swords
and that steel to the western people
became known as damascus steel or syriac
steel or whatever
but it was imported into syria from
india
so just like the people in europe
called
the decimal system and the numbers
arabic numerals even though they had
come from india similarly this steel
which was manufactured in india was
given the name of damascus steel because
they came across this steel first in
damascus
so this technology is called crucible
steel technology it involves the
infusion of carbon
into the steel there is a whole process
that was involved in this we have lost
the process
we have lost the method
okay there is all kinds of speculation
that there was a certain kind of
chemistry and certain temperatures and
all that
and you use quenching while forging
which is you dump the the
steel into water and quench it or you
can dump it into snow if you want or
whatever right
so that there's a whole process that you
follow while
while uh
while forging any
steel implement or weapon or whatever
but
it was all done using a certain kind of
steel
that was manufactured only in india only
indians had this technology
and then these big
steel ingots would be exported to
various countries wherever they were in
demand and those people there the
blacksmith there the classes the craft
smiths there would then forge that steel
into various implements or weapons or
whatever they wanted daggers swords
and whatever else
but that steel came from india the
syrians the the people there did not
know how to make that
particular kind of steel so this
technology is called crucible steel it
is at least 2500 years old and the
oldest evidence we have found
the oldest archaeological evidence we
have found
of this steel being manufactured in
india dates back to about 2500 years
before today and the oldest evidence is
found in present-day tamil nadu and sri
lanka
so that's where the technology
seems to have emerged from of course we
have done very little archaeology in
india so maybe if we
do more we may find evidence of it in
other parts of india as well possibly
perhaps
but thus far
the oldest evidence we have is from
southern india from sri lanka in tamil
nadu
and it is about two and a half thousand
years old so it is undeniably an indian
product an indian technology
the syrians did not know how to
manufacture
or to produce that kind of steel they
only knew how to
buy the steel and then use it to forge
various implements
so that is the truth about damascus
steel it is not damascus steel it is
indian steel
okay kunal says what are your thoughts
on the gujarat government's decision to
include the srimad-bhagavad-gita in the
school syllabus
thumbs up great job this should be taken
up all across the country we need to be
taught our culture our history
systematically from a young age
we have we have been deracinated the
past few generations we are completely
cut off from our culture from our
cultural heritage the heritage of
thousands of generations of our
ancestors
and because of that indians today are
lost they're adrift
and they don't and they see their own
culture as something that is other
i am not a practicing hindu i am hindu
only in name i never go to temple blah
blah blah blah blah
it is not the fault of today's indians
that they are like this it's because
they have been systematically cut off
from their roots
so what the gujarat government has done
the decision is an excellent decision i
would like to see this replicated all
across india not only okay the the
bhagavad-gita is a good start
but we need to be taught our culture
systematically properly
in a step-by-step manner from ages
whatever until you become an adult that
would be really good why not it's your
own culture why should you not be taught
it
all right this is by shivang
greetings from kanada i am an indian
international student living in canada
for people like me channels like yours
are the main source of information
and watching a podcast is fun like
watching a netflix show huge one thank
you so much sir thank you appreciate it
my question is in 1971 war if russia
would not have helped us by sending a
nuclear submarines and using veto at all
the crucial moments then according to
you what would have happened to india
is there a chance that our whole
geography would have been different if
they hadn't helped
is this the main reason why indians
today have a soft spot for russia
what would have been the worst scenario
for india if russia had not helped okay
so what happened in 1971 in 1971 there
was this ongoing genocide in east
pakistan present-day bangladesh the
pakistani army was murdering
tens of thousands hundreds of thousands
millions
of innocent men women and children
bengalis
irrespective of their religion of course
most of them were hindus they were
targeting hindus but anybody who helped
them was also targeted
intellectuals were targeted
or anybody who has a higher education
degree was targeted
so they were trying to wipe out the
flower
the cream of the crop of the people of
bengal and they were trying to eradicate
hinduism once and for once and for all
from bengal
right so the genocide which was going on
over there
would have consumed would have
killed between
1 million and 5 million five million
bengalis
the official figure is i don't know what
the official figures are don't believe
the official figures they are always
under representations of what really
happened
so there was this genocide going on and
millions of bengalis were running for
their lives and where would they go they
had nowhere to go except cross over into
india
because when things go bad no matter
where you are from you want to go to
india today even afghans want to come to
india now they will recognize india as
their
as the only nation that can save them
so
they these bengalis millions of them
they were streaming into india trying to
escape from the horrific genocide that
was going on there
so eventually this became an enormous
burden for
for india they were coming into assam
they were coming into bengal and so on
so forth how could india feed so many
people and sustain such an enormous
influx of refugees when india at that
time was still an incredibly war country
and then what happened is that the
pakistanis from east pakist
military operation
into east pakistan and to defeat the
west pakistan army and liberate the
country from the
from the force that was
conducting genocide
so india retaliated
once the pakistani military action began
then what happened
is that the u.s government under nixon
and and the secretary of state
henry kissinger they decided to
intervene on behalf of the pakistanis so
the united states supported the ongoing
genocide in in bangladesh in east bengal
the americans were on the side of
genocide
they decided to take military action to
allow the genocide to go on
and they were aware of what's happening
read the book the blood telegram
they were aware the american government
was very well aware of what the
pakistanis were doing and they were fine
with that
so now that india starts this military
operation
what the americans do is they send an
entire aircraft carrier
task force into
the sea of kalinga the bay of bengal
to intimidate india and to threaten
india because that aircraft carrier
would have
dozens of fighter planes with lots of
arms and ammunition they could
possibly obliterate parts of india with
that
and it's not just one aircraft carrier
it's an entire
strike group with lots of uh destroyers
a few submarines and all that so that
was designed to intimidate india
and and they were
stopped and they were prevented from
doing this because the russians sent a
fleet of nuclear submarines to the same
place so when the americans arrived into
the bay of bengal they were met
by russian
nuclear submarines and that's why they
had to back off
they sent the uss enterprise to india
but it was met by this
waiting task force of russian nuclear
submarines and that's why they had to
back off otherwise what would have
happened the question is had the
russians not helped india out what would
have happened
the americans would have interfered
militarily
india i suppose at the time was no match
for the american
uh
the aircraft carrier type
task force strike group that they'd send
to india it would have had enormous
firepower they could have broken india
into pieces possibly they could have cut
off
more parts of india maybe the the far
east of india the so-called
northeast of india possibly they could
have done that
they would have certainly
tried to humiliate india and break india
further into pieces
so what is the worst case scenario for
india
you would have seen a pakistani victory
over india
and if the pakistani
army would have prevailed in east
pakistan maybe the pakistani army in
west pakistan may also have been
encouraged to go further and try to take
over the rest of kashmir and maybe even
strike for delhi because that's always
been the great dream of the pakistani
army we'll have lunch in jaipur and
dinner in delhi that sort of thing that
has been the great dream of theirs
so possibly
had the russians not stopped the
american
aircraft carrier group
such things may have happened
so essentially you can say that the
russians
saved india by sending
their nuclear submarines
to con to confront the american aircraft
carrier in this
group
task force whatever you call it
so it's possible like you say shivang
that our geography would have been
completely different maybe india would
have been broken into pieces had the
russians not intervened and helped india
out
and of course the russians always
supported india in the u.n security
council by using their veto power
whenever it was necessary it was the
ussr that did that
so as you know as you can see there is
this long history that india has
with the ussr or russia where they have
helped india out
on multiple locations on a continuing
recurring basis it's not a one-off thing
now of course they were doing it
to further their own national interest
that's how it works in geopolitics
there's no free lunch
so they were helping india because it
was beneficial for them fine
that is okay that's how it works but
they help india so that is the reason
why many indians apparently have a soft
spot for russia that is certainly
especially in the older generations the
people who were born in the 60s and 70s
of all that maybe some of them have a
soft spot for russia because they've
seen the russians help india when all
the odds were stacked against india
i mean there was a make or break
moment a make or break
episode in india's history had the
americans actually used the military
option against india it could have
broken india
an aircraft carrier strike group is a
massively powerful
military deployment
it has more power than most countries
have
right
and in the 1970s aircraft carriers were
almost invulnerable
cruise missiles did not exist at the
time
today india can take out any aircraft
carrier strike group using the brahmos
missiles you fire a num
if you know what is the mathematical
threshold of defense then you can fire
just one more missile and you're gonna
breach the defenses it's just a
mathematical certainty that you can
obliterate an entire aircraft carrier
strike group using cruise missiles but
that technology did not exist in the
1970s and india was very poor at the
time
so that was a make or break moment for
india and russia intervened when india
needed it
so had that not happened india could
have been destroyed broken
into pieces
and maybe india would have been some
parts of india would have been under
pakistani rule today
so that's what the americans intended
for india
and they
were foiled
by russia
adinat says can india get get access to
cutting-edge technology like the f-35
from the u.s
the u.s wants india to buy f-35 and
every
all kinds of other
weapons systems from them
which is not advisable first of all the
f-35 is is
an overpriced piece of garbage
let me not mince my words the f-35 is
incredibly expensive more than 100
million dollars per per piece
and it is garbage it's not a good
fighter aircraft it does nothing
it it is supposed to be a multi-role
fighter aircraft that has vertical take
off capabilities and all it's never been
tested in actual combat
and
from whatever i have studied about this
particular
aircraft design
it's not
worth the price tag and it's not it
doesn't have any special capabilities it
has a certain amount of stealth features
and all
i think the f22 raptor is a far better
aircraft in my opinion but it doesn't
have certain features that this new
aircraft the f-35 supposedly has so the
so the
the japanese are buying f-35s very
expensive planes
the japan the japanese are a u.s vassal
state the israelis are buying f-35s the
israelis are a u.s vasal state the turks
were supposed to buy f-35s but the
americans have refused now because the
turks bought a piece of equipment from
russia the s-400
system
so the americans
you will know that when the americans
sell the f-35 to a nation that nation is
in one way or the other directly or
indirectly an american vassal state
right
so
i don't think that technology is worth
it even if they offer it to us at half
the price it may not be worth it because
first of all you would need to integrate
your military
capabilities to a very deep extent
with the american military which means
that you to open up your bandwidth and
various things
to
to their
uh
system which would give them a great
deal of access deep into
your military systems and a great deal
of insight into what you're actually
actually doing
it will essentially make your plans
and your military completely transparent
to the americans and that's not
in
india's interest so yes india can get
get access to the f-35 technology to the
u.s by
becoming a u.s vassal state
otherwise they will not give it to us i
would say that we don't need the f-35
for the price of an f-35 which is about
i don't know how much it is how much how
much does it cost
in excess of a hundred million dollars
maybe 120 let's let's say 120
you could acquire three or four
pages class aircraft maybe five of those
for the price of one f-35
quantity has a quality of its own please
understand that the pages is not a bad
bad aircraft of course this is these are
two different class of aircrafts their
roles are different and all i'm just
giving an example what india must do is
india must invest the money
in developing its own indigenous
family of fighter aircraft a twin engine
deck based fighter the tedbf
an advanced medium combat aircraft amca
a fifth generation aircraft in various
other classes of aircraft that's what
india needs to do don't waste your money
and buying products from other countries
that will then be remote controlled by
those countries
instead of that develop your own systems
they just says why didn't chalukyas and
pratiharas help prathera johan in the
second battle of the rhine
did other hindu kingdoms not care about
what was happening in other kingdoms
how was mahmoud of ghazni able to ride
freely sumnat temple and destroyed it
what were the cholas and pandias doing
what was king bhoj mir both doing
i'm studying this history recently
please click correct correct me if i am
wrong okay so you have spoken about a
lot of different kingdoms
and dynasties from across india you're
talking about two different time periods
ghazni is before
and the gory is after so let me give you
a big picture answer
a bird's eye overview of what was
happening without going into specifics
at that period of time
india was not unified under a single
uh
central command
when you had the mauryan empire under
lord chandragupta maurya under ashok
mori etc we had unified control over the
entire subcontinent from one place
under the
kushan empire under lord kanishka
the whole of india was unified under a
central rule the same thing you saw
during the gupta era
and during the chola area also you had
some of it but it was mostly in southern
parts of india
the southern half of india and the whole
of southeast asia
and of course under people like under
emperor
also you had most of india was unified
so when you have
a unified
geopolitical entity the whole of the
subcontinent is unified under one
central leadership
that's when if an invader comes any
foray or incursion into any part of
india will be dealt with with the
combined force of the whole
subcontinent
that's what happens but when you have
political fragmentation
then if you invade one part of india
then only the local king who is in
charge or ruling that part of india will
respond that's how it goes
so there was a lack of political unity
in this period of time when you talk
about the invasion of this guy
mahmoud of ghazni or the battle of taran
under gori india was disunited india was
fragmented into small pieces small
kingdoms and all of these kingdoms
they were the same people of course but
they had these petty rivalries with each
other so if some kind of misfortune
befalls one of them the others would see
it as a political advantage for them and
therefore they would not interfere and
they would let let the misfortune
continue and the the thinking or the
calculation was that if something goes
bad with this guy
maybe in the long run it'll it'll it'll
be advantageous to me politically maybe
it will help me extend
my my kingdom or get more political
benefits from this
so
and they did not know they did not have
the benefit of hindsight
today
we know what the intentions of these
turks
were
it was not simply
military conquest
it was not simply plunder it was not
simply
the annexation of a kingdom it was the
complete cultural genocide of india that
they thought they sought to enslave
millions of indians women children in
most horrific ways to ship them off to
central asia and to the west western
parts beyond
india and persia
and use them in all kinds of horrific
degrading ways
as slaves
and they sought to destroy india's
culture civilization and religions
that's what this ought to do at that
time our local petty kings and
chieftains did not know this
right and therefore it was not so it was
not seen as a threat to dharma
it was just seen as some invader coming
in harassing one of my rivals so let it
happen oh no
and the cholas in the cholas at the time
were dealing with southeast asia they
had an enormous maritime empire there
and therefore maybe they did not even
know perhaps possibly what was happening
in the northern part of india and they
were confident and secure in the in the
knowledge that they were incredibly
powerful and they could deal with
anything so if it comes here we'll deal
with it until that time let it be it's
not my problem so that is the kind of
unfortunate thinking that was there that
is what happens when you have political
disunity your political fragmentation
and that's why i always keep saying
that when you have a nation that is
at the scale of a subcontinent you need
very strong central leadership
the nation has to be administered
centrally right now in 21st century
india you have too much democracy too
much federalism
each of the states has too much power
and many of the states are acting
against the national interest in a
variety of ways i will not give you
specifics because i don't want to get
into that controversy but i think if you
have the half a brain you'll know what
i'm talking about
so that's the situation that's the kind
of situation you had a thousand years
ago and that's why the other hindu
kingdoms they knew what was happening
they didn't care they said honey though
it is good for us because it's bad for
him
in the long run we will benefit so they
allowed it to happen
which is not the kind
which is the kind of petty approach that
destroys civilizations
so
so at that time
none of these kingdoms none of these
kings or chieftains thought on a
subcontinental civilizational scale
unfortunately
so that's why all these things happened
druid says some linguistic experts say
that the sanskrit language along with
the brahmi script came from the aramaic
language is there some truth to this
so
these so-called linguistic experts they
say that the brahmi script emerged from
the semitic aramaic script they don't
refer to the sanskrit language a
language is different from a script a
script is different from a language
a script is a vehicle
that carries a language
so when it comes to the sanskrit script
you can write the sanskrit script
the sanskrit language i
beg your pardon when it comes to the
sanskrit language you can write sanskrit
in devanagari in brahmi in the
devanagari script in the brahma script
in the karoshi script in the sharda
script in any script that you want any
script that is suitable for indian
languages you can even write sanskrit in
the travel script if you wish it's
perfectly suitable for that
so a script is separate from a language
a script is simply a medium that carries
the language
now let's talk about the brahmi script
many of these so-called linguists most
of the the linguists they claim that the
brahmi script emerged from the ancient
aramaic script which is from the middle
east
it's a semitic script what proof do they
have up for this none whatsoever it's
all conjecture it's all speculation and
they have come across they have come
they have created this
this kind of uh
situation by arriving at a so-called
consensus so a group of people come
together and they all say okay we agree
on this and that's how it becomes a law
so linguistics is a non-scientific
discipline
it should be scientific
when
panini who is the father of linguistics
wrote his great treaties
it was entirely scientific it was
entirely entirely logical and
algorithmic
unfortunately today's linguists are more
into politics and consensus building and
there is very little scientific or
logical basis to the claims that they
make
and all of these so-called eminent
linguists who have who have
decided that brahmi is descended from
aramaic they're all from the west and
they have a few indian minions
boot lickers who are part of that group
so we need to reject this nonsensical
claim
there is no evidence
that brahmi came from aramaic there is
no evidence that links the two scripts
together
there is no hard undeniable undisputable
evidence there is very little tangential
evidence even
that links brahmi from aramaic it's just
conjecture and speculation
but they have created a group and they
have decided what's what what is the
what is the facts and what's not which
is nonsense
most likely the brahmi script
evolved from the ancient
saraswati sindhu script
the various inscriptions that are still
undeciphered that you find in the
saraswatis in the region from about five
thousand six thousand years before today
maybe seven thousand
years before today
that script which was in use at that
time
it is most likely the script that
eventually slowly evolved
into the brahmi script
so that is the most likely
that happened
but what needs to happen today in india
is we need to
create
our own institutes of linguistics
and we need to employ young linguists
who have not been influenced by all this
nonsense and we need to do an a priori
uh
undertaking
and we need to examine all of these
things from an a priori basis based on
only logic not based on other people's
interpretations and opinions so that's
what needs to happen but most likely
99.999
brahmi has nothing to do to to do with
the aramaic script brahmi most likely
is
a temporal evolution
of the old saraswati sindhu
script
everyone knows foreign aid is just
another form of bribery india should not
take money from the uk love from
great britain
so they call it aid
the west whether it's the us whether
it's
the uk or any other western country they
give money to various so-called
developing countries and they call it
aid and assistance but you know what
it's not really it like
like is being said here
in
the in our indian cultural context we
have this this idea of don
when you give dhan
to somebody whether it's to a country or
to an institution an organization or a
temple or whatever
that don has no strings attached
you give the money to them because you
feel that they are doing some good work
and your financial contribution will
help in that good cause so you give the
money as dhana
and then the organization or the country
or whoever it is will decide what to do
what what is the best way of using that
money you leave it to them
right so that is done dhana means money
or aid given with no expectation of
anything in return
right no reciprocation i'm giving it to
you and you use it that's it that's all
i want
when the waste gives aid
there are all kinds of conditions
attached all kinds of strings attached
and what those conditions and strings
are it's interference in your internal
affairs
so let's say you go to a loan to the
world bank the imf they will give you a
loan but they will also tell you
that i'm giving you this money now i'm
going to tell you how to use the money
you can use it any way you want we're
going to tell you exactly specifically
how you use it
you're gonna allow these many ngos to
come up in your country you're gonna
open up your your economy to my country
to these many sectors you're gonna allow
this much percentage of investment and
people can from other countries can come
and acquire land and companies in your
country so they're gonna infiltrate your
country deep down
and that is foreign interference so this
aid is poisonous money it's poisoned
money we don't want that sort of money
and india doesn't receive any foreign
anymore it is the uk that insists on
sending a few million dollars per year
to certain ngos
which don't do anything for the
upliftment or the betterment of india
it is all done to further their
geopolitical objectives long-term
geopolitical objectives so any aid that
comes from the west is used is utilized
only to further the long-term
geopolitical objectives of the western
world it does nothing
to benefit
developing nations see what's happening
in africa they have been sending in aid
to africa for decades
africa is still the same
much of that aid
is used as salaries of ngo personnel the
biggest ngo scam is the un
just see the kind of salaries these un
officials enjoy
incredibly high salaries they travel by
private jets all of that money that is
in the u.n is supposed to be used for
the betterment of the world but most of
it is used in these salaries and all
these perks
so
foreign aid is poisoned money it works
against your country against your
national interest it furthers the
long-term geopolitical objectives of the
country where it comes from at the
expense of your long-term geopolitical
interests and this applies not only to
india but it applies to all developing
countries no matter where they are
whether it is pakistan whether sri lanka
whether it is kenya whether it is
anywhere in africa or anywhere else
do not take foreign aid
develop good reciprocal relationships
with like-minded countries
and
relationships that are of a mutually
beneficial nature
that is how it's supposed to be
don't ever take foreign aid it's gonna
just hurt you and harm you
okay
please give insights on how the chinese
acquired israel's larvae aircraft
technology thereby creating its own
j-10c variant
uncanny resemblance let's take a look at
what
these aircraft are like
so the israeli let's talk about the
israeli larvae is
okay let me share my screen
what does that aircraft look like
so the israeli lavi aircraft looks like
this it is a derivative of the american
f-16 aircraft
so that's uh what this aircraft is they
used some
they use the american f16 as the basis
for creating this israeli variant
so the larvae is essentially the israeli
version
a slightly enhanced and modified version
of the american f-16 aircraft from the
1970s
it's a good aircraft as you can see if
you know what the f-16 looks like it
looks like similar to this
there is this air intake for the
jet and all that so this is the israeli
level now let's take it take a look at
the chinese
j-10
data fighter
it looks like a modified version of the
larvae
doesn't it
the resemblance like the comment says
over here
is uncanny
and it's it's therefore it's it's quite
clear that there is some sort of a
familial
relationship between the lobby and the
in the chinese
jaitan jaitensi
there clearly is
so if you look at the history of this
chinese fighter jet i think the
development was
flagged off in the early 1980s
and
it took
10 15 20 years for the aircraft to be
developed i think it was inducted into
the chinese air force in the late in the
mid or late 2000s between 2003 or 2000
and 2010 somewhere there okay you can
look up the exact details if you're
interested
and people have alleged that the chinese
somehow acquired israeli inputs israeli
technology
to create this aircraft the j-10 which
was at the time the most advanced
aircraft the chinese had
it is still in operation they have more
than 500 of these aircraft that are
still in operation or that have been
built
so that's a big number
so what's the what's the truth
see the israelis were very interested
in china as a market for their defense
equipment
the israelis have this reasonably
advanced quite advanced defense
manufacturing industry they manufacture
all kinds of defense equipment
aircraft tanks
missiles and other things lots of other
things
and china is a big market for this so
the israelis were very interested in the
chinese market they
had good relations with china with the
chinese communist party
and they wanted to sell all kinds of
stuff to the chinese it is the americans
who vetoed
this israeli move the americans
prevented
israel from
taking such a relationship further and
making it a big relationship
because the americans know what the
child by that time of the americans
had understood what china's real
objectives are the chinese objective is
to replace and displace the us as the
global superpower so that would be a big
threat to the us if israeli technology
made its way into chinese hands but
apparently it looks like this aircraft's
technology
had already made its way into the
chinese hands
so most likely the israelis supplied
their
larvae aircraft technology blueprints
designs whatever it was to the chinese
of course for a fee
and that's how the chinese were able to
develop this
jaitan
aircraft
so the israelis were very interested in
china when the chinese market was off
limits to them because of their american
masters
that's when they developed this this
this good relationship with india
because india is also a huge market for
defense equipment
and india and israel are cooperating to
a large extent right now in a variety of
ways in in terms of defense equipment
but their original objective their
original goal was to
uh
get into the chinese market
so that's how
you see this uncanny resemblance between
these two very different
aircraft
swarup says the ministry of defense has
added
101 additional items to its list of
defense related equipment that cannot be
imported from foreign countries this is
the third list issued by the ministry
pushing the overall tally of such
equipment to 310
import restrictions for on defense
equipment are aimed to promote
the indigenous defense manufacturing
sector in india these items will
henceforth be procured from local
sources as per the provisions
of defense acquisition procedure dap
2020 your thoughts
very good
i have always been saying that india
needs to completely indigenize its
defense
sector
all of our defense equipment whether it
is whether it is rifles
light rifles ak-47 type rifles
or
heavy machine guns
anti-aircraft guns bow force type uh
weaponry
aircraft submarines ships whatever it is
or life
and what is it bulletproof vests
whatever it is all of it needs to be
manufactured in india when you import
equipment from others there are all
kinds of strings and conditions attached
yesterday in the other podcast i spoke
about how lots of these these this
equipment can be remote controlled by
the original equipment manufacturer
certain features can be disabled on
demand on command and you may be left
with a piece of equipment or aircraft or
whatever that doesn't work it doesn't do
what you need it to do
so it is very important
it's very important for india to
completely indigenize its defense
manufacturing industry everything needs
to be manufactured in india so these
steps that are currently being taken by
the government of india are
a welcome move and a very important move
in that direction
so i think it's a very good thing that
the government is doing
and it needs to be continued further
over the years in a step-by-step manner
in a phased deployment
manner you first take a number of things
that you can already manufacture in
india and make it uh and prohibit any
import of that then wait for a few years
and wait for your industry to mature
then a whole other set of items can now
be manufactured in india so you prohibit
the import of that so you do that step
by step over a few years and then
eventually in the next two decades
hopefully you have a completely
indigenous defense industry that can
actually export
weapons and weapon systems to other
countries which would be a great source
of revenue and foreign exchange and and
it would boost india's gdp so that is
the overall objective
hopefully in the next two decades in the
next 20 years we can completely
indigenize our defense industry which
would be fantastic
wenzel says thank you for all this
information
great podcast looking tomorrow looking
forward to more thank you sir
your thoughts on india having only one
nuclear submarine should india and
france form an alliance to develop
nuclear nuclear submarines which would
be a great advantage for the indian navy
as of today
so we had this nuclear submarine called
the ins chakra
on lees on a 10 year release from russia
it's an akula class
nuclear submarine
and that's the second akula class that
in at least the second i think that
india had taken on a 10 year lease
that's been given back to russia
it was rather old it served its purpose
so that nuclear sub is now gone
will we take another nuclear sub from
the russians on lease that remains to be
seen
do we have any operational nuclear
submarines we have the ins arihant which
is fully deployed which is fully
operational and we also have the ins
arigath
which may or may not be fully
operational fully deployed it was
undergoing sea trials and all that
which means it was already capable of
sailing in the sea under the under the
sea
it was undergoing extended extensive
seat trials
now has it been operationalized or not
we don't quite know maybe it has maybe
it's not been operationalized maybe it
will be announced in the future that it
was operational from so and so date the
way it was done with the ins arihant so
as far as i see it
we most likely have two operational
nuclear submarines
so what are the capabilities of the
submarines they have indigenous nuclear
reactors within them which power them
and that essentially gives your
submarine the ability to stay submerged
indefinitely for months on end
now it depends on the specifics of your
submarine your technology the maturity
and all that
every new submarine that we build
will be an iterative improvement on the
previous submarine so we had the ins
arihant which had a certain size certain
capability the ins arigath will be an
iterative improvement upon the ins
arihant
so the exact
dimensions of the new submarine the
arigath are classified they have not
been revealed to the press to the world
and its weapons capabilities are also
kind of
not completely clearly known which is a
good thing so the ins ari hunt can
carry a certain number of
k
what is it there are two classes of k
missiles
one is a
medium-range missile and one is a
long-range missile so i think the ins
arihant is capable of carrying a certain
number
of those
medium-range sagarika missiles
the ins aright can also carry
a similar number possibly of those
missiles and possibly
an enhanced range long range version of
those missiles which
have been under development
apparently for a few years maybe they
have been deployed we don't know and we
should not know about this that at this
stage so as far as i am concerned we
have two
deployed operational nuclear submarines
at various stages of deployment
so that to some extent completes our
nuclear triad the question is should
india and france form an alliance to
develop nuclear symbols we already have
the technology now we already have two
nuclear subs that are in the ocean
are operational
so we don't need
uh
a transfer of technology from the french
the french have a mature nuclear
submarine program they have been using
nuclear submarines for four years for
decades
so have the russians the russians have
actually in a variety of ways
helped india
with the nuclear submarine technology
especially the miniaturization of the
nuclear reactor
it's perfectly easy to create a large
big
bloaty wheeled or unwieldy nuclear
reactor that takes up a lot of space
but to have the same nuclear reactor the
same power output
in a miniaturized design that is where
you need advances in technology
and that is apparently where russia has
helped india with the miniaturization of
nuclear reactor technology so that you
can take a nuclear reactor that's which
which is a powerful nuclear reactor and
fit it inside a submarine
so india now has the technology of
course it is still a work in progress
every new nuclear subway build will have
an improved version of the reactor and
various other things so i think india is
doing very well india doesn't need help
from anybody else at this stage now
um
so we we have a good relationship with
france it's you could call it a
strategic relationship the french are
part of nato but they are not a us
vasal state they have their own
independent foreign policy which the
americans don't like very much
but that's just how it is so india and
france have a very good relationship
very cordial relationship our strategic
interests align to a large extent our
national interests align to a
significant extent especially in the
indo-pacific region france whether you
know it or not is a major indian ocean
military power
france has multiple indian ocean
possessions which means islands that are
part of france
so it is beneficial for france to
cooperate with india and vice versa
so we have
cooperation military cooperation
strategic cooperation at various levels
with the french the most visible
aspect of which is the acquisition of
rafal fighter aircraft
so we could explore certain cooperation
when it comes to technology whether
whether it is jet engine technology or
something else
but as far as the nuclear program
nuclear submarine program goes india is
already on the right track it will take
time
maybe 10 20 years for us to have a much
more mature
nuclear submarine program but unless we
do the trial and end error right now
that won't happen so we are on the right
track we need to continue on that
okay arnob says i'm master student
economics with a keen interest in
geopolitics i have a few chinese friends
they are good people yeah of course
chinese are good people i have nothing
against the chinese people i have known
chinese people they are all nice people
our discussions become a bit awkward
when we discuss politics
i defend my country in all aspects but i
lose in one certain point they say arnab
you say india had a glorious ancient
past was one of the richest nations
in terms of wealth culture and so on but
why is india so poor nowadays and i
don't have a counter argument why aren't
why don't you have a counter argument so
as an economic student i know our
situation in poverty
and i cannot pull put all the blame on
the invaders and colonizers i'd like to
hear your take on why we are so
dreadfully bad
whilst our ancestors were so amazingly
great
do you think the rishis would be proud
of us seeing us in our present condition
they would not be proud of us now let's
see why we are in the situation
you look at the gdp of india as a
percentage of the world's gdp it was up
to it was
at least 33 percent of the entire world
gdp ahead of china until the 1700s
and then it crashes precipitously what
happened the british destroyed india's
economy they destroyed india's
industrial system india was the first
industrialized civilization in the world
they destroyed all of india's indigenous
industry industries
everything and they took all of our
treasure our wealth our gold everything
of value back to england and they
destroyed india in every single way
that is why india is so poor you may
have the richest cult culture if you
don't have a correspondingly powerful
military
that can defend your culture then that
culture having that great culture is
pointless
so yes we were rich but we
there came a time when india was
politically disunited
fragmented like i've spoken about in the
past even today and that's why
foreigners were able to invade and
occupy us and destroy our economy so
it's very simple
why can't you put the blame on what
really happened
it is because the invaders and
colonizers destroyed india
our ancestors
did not have political unity at the time
and that's why this happened
but it is these invaders and colonizers
who destroyed india thoroughly it is
completely
on them what happened
the genocide of 100 million indians plus
by the british it's a known fact you
just add up the tally of the famines
that they engineered year after year
after year that itself is gonna give you
a figure close to 100 million plus 10
million that they killed after 1857 in
the in the years after 1857.
so overall they killed more than 100
million indians at least 100 million
then they destroyed the entire economy
they destroyed the industry the various
indigenous industries and they took away
all the wealth
and that's why the west is prosperous
they are enjoying the fruits of the
wealth they stole from india
and from england
that wealth dispersed all across europe
and the u.s
have you heard of yale university yale
the guy
after whom the university is named
was an east india company official in
india
he plundered a lot of wealth it became
his personal fortune and that was the
basis of the yale college which is now
yale university
so a lot of the wealth that was stolen
from india made its way
into north america and built
what is now known as the united states
and parts of canada and so on so that's
what happened that is why india is so
poor and after 18 after 1947 the
government that was put in place was not
a democratically elected government it
was a transfer of power from one set of
crooks to another set of crooks
and the system
that we have in india after 1947 is the
same as the british raj system
the laws are the same
the language is the same the bureaucracy
is the same the institutions are the
same so it's like we are still colonized
so india could have risen very rapidly
after 1947 it did not happen because we
had the great magnificent shri
jawaharlal nehru in place and he is not
a reflection of the people of india
he was
undemocratically
put in place as the prime minister of
india
so what
happened is not something that was
in the hands of the people of india now
china
is very different from india so nice
blah blah blah they were very very lucky
that the people who conquered their
lands
did not have the evil
pernicious malicious mindset of the
westerners and the turks
had changed khan
wanted
to extract all wealth out of china
china would way be behind india today
he would have done such a thorough job
of extracting wealth out of china there
would have been nothing left in china
but he chose not to do that it was his
magnanimity that saved china and
enriched china
so had the mongols
had a colonial mindset then mongolia
would be the richest country in the
world today but they're not
you see that's what happened
so the chinese were invaded multiple
times but they got really lucky that the
mongols did not destroy china the way
the turks and the british destroyed
india
there was this
period of humiliation the chinese called
the 100 years the century of humiliation
when
western powers did certain
nasty
activities in china
well again the chinese got lucky that
the western powers were not able to
thoroughly colonize china things
events that happened in the world
prevented
the western powers from colonizing china
the way they colonized india again if
the west had colonized china the way
they colonized india china would have
been in the same situation that india is
in right now so the chinese
if they are
currently in a better position in india
it's because of dumb luck
nothing else they are in no way superior
to india
indian culture has enriched them for
2000 years
india has exported culture
india has been a net exporter of culture
to china
india civilized china to a large extent
whether you like it or not so that is
what you need to tell your chinese
friends my dear friend arnab
okay anish says indians never invaded
any country ever how true is this
statement is it a way of making indians
weak is it something to be proud of and
so on so forth
and in the future
should it remain the same
as if it is our obligation to not invade
a country
uh have you heard of kanishka the great
many people say he was chinese what
nonsense
what utter nonsense he did more than any
other emperor almost any other emperor
to promote and enrich india and indian
culture in
an incredible variety of ways so he was
one of our greatest emperors they did
not invade and conquer
the whole of central asia
his kingdom stretched from the aral to
the caspian sea into
all of northern india and western india
and eastern india and parts of the
deccan plateau as well
then
he also invaded what is now called as
xinjiang in china
and reconquered the territory of his
ancestors
because that's where his ancestors lived
a few centuries before they were the
indo-european or indian origin tushar
people takarians koshans
so
india invaded all these lands
what's wrong with that
look at the great emperor
did he not conquer central asia again
did he not conquer bahalika bulk
and parts of tibet he did
so
once again indians invaded and conquered
what about the great chulas
first raja raja chola who conquered sri
lanka all chilean has always been part
of india anyway but
today it's not part of india so he went
and conquered that that island and he
conquered parks some other parts of
burma etc and then his son rajendra
chola who conquered the whole of
southeast asia all the way up to the
philippines
right so were they not indians
so
these claims that india never invaded
any country they are absolute banker i
could go back before the more in era
also
and you have the so-called yamnaya
invaders
whose genes are found all across eastern
western central europe
every european more or less is a
descendant of these indian origin
invaders
so that is all nonsense that india has
never invaded any any country there are
so many examples
of indian
invasions in other lands and is it our
obligation to not invade a country in
the future no
i believe when the time is right india
should invade
other countries when there are just
causes for war
when you have just causes for war then
war is justifiable
like when the pakistanis attacked india
in 1914 1971
when they launched bombing raids via
their so-called air force in 1971 that
gave india a just cause for going to war
with pakistan and that's when 1971
happened in bangladesh was liberated so
whenever there is a just cause for war
or whenever
it suits our national interest we should
invade i think it is
in the coming years and decades india
needs a couple of wars
because indians have this attitude or
this this
this loser mentality
we need a couple of wars and victories
to get rid of that attitude so i think
in the future it should happen it needs
to happen but when there is a reasonable
justifiable cause of war or when it is
something that suits that that is in
line
with india's national interest i am by
no means of war monger i would love
nothing more than global peace in bhai
chara what so they have a become and all
that thing but that that's not how the
world works i am also a realistic person
so that's what i what i have to say
about this
anime says is it true that ancient
dharmic people did not believe in right
written form of documentation
they had auditory learning smriti
methods to be passed from one generation
to another
script came very late in our
civilization which is actually
non-dharmic by yeah
so that's what some people say
in a recent argument i tried to cite the
reference of the horse training manual
by kikuli
but my point was rule out who ruled out
your point bring them to me
so my point was ruled out by saying 3500
years old inscription is too recent for
reverse civilization your thoughts
see
our civilization is very old yet three
and a half thousand years ago if
something happened it is very recent of
course in the grand scale
in the grand chronology of india
civilization that's true
now this claim that people make that
india did not believe in written
documentation do they have any evidence
for this
no
of course there are very few records
that you find in india of ancient
writings and all we have the saraswati
hindu script which is very ancient 5000
years old or so maybe more
so that is one example of documentation
of some inscriptions but that doesn't we
still don't know what it says so you
could kind of say
we still don't know what it is so let's
not consider that and again
cool is horse training manual in c in
present-day syria which is written in
the local language with
certain terms in sanskrit because those
terms were not available in the local
language it tells you that it was a guy
who whose native language was sanskrit
but it's only three and a half thousand
years old
and that's in syria it's not in india so
it is indians who live there so it
doesn't matter it does it is not uh
applicable again
so what is true see first of all
when the greeks came to the court of
chandragupta maurya
they
noticed and they have noted this they've
recorded this that
the indians
had
a calendar
that went back
six thousand something years before that
time
so the more in era was let's say roughly
2500 years before today
add another 6 000 years to that that is
8 500 years before today that's how old
the calendar was
and indians had
recorded written lineages of kings that
dated back to that time that is eight
and a half thousand years before today
so is that not something that was
documented at the time we have lost
their records today but we have
the documented evidence from the greeks
who said they have seen these records
and these records existed
so there is one piece of evidence that
totally demolishes this claim that
indians did not believe in any
documentation
secondly
you have so many translations that are
available
in chinese in tibetan
in
present day
which were which were discovered in
parts of china
in parts of present-day xinjiang region
of so-called
of of china chinese occupied region in
present-day tibet in other parts of
central you have so many translations
of ancient indian texts that have been
docu that have been discovered in all
these regions north of india these were
translations from sanskrit
of older
texts
right so that tells you that there was a
copious amount of sanskrit literature
whether it is buddhist literature or or
hindu literature or jain literature
doesn't matter this was all the
civilizational corpus of ancient india
that the chinese the tibetans were so
deeply interested in that they
translated all of that into into
chinese and into the gandhari language
which was prevalent in central asia and
so on
so that again demonstrates that there
were written records the documentations
of various things
and
we also know
that
india had
great universities
all across the length and the breadth of
the indian subcontinent
right we know nalanda the sheila nalanda
is in the far east texas in the far west
and so many more
vikramashiela udantapuri
um
sharda pete and and many many many many
many more too many to to
recount over here
and we also know that the turks
destroyed all of these universities and
burned all of the libraries the
university library at nalanda is known
to have burned for months
so what what was burned there was it not
documentation that was burned
right
so
based on all of these facts that we know
about one can conclude
that indians
had extensive documentation that dated
back thousands of years
what was burned in those fires a
thousand years before today was the
records of thousands of years of indian
history and science and what much more
so we had documentation it was destroyed
by the turks we are left with very
little today even today in various
temples and all there are all these palm
leaf palm leaf manuscripts and other
manuscripts that are still gathering
dust
they have not been
preserved
they are all under the asi which is
doing nothing they should have been
digitized and
preserved through some means
so there are millions of manuscripts
that still exist which is all ancient
documentation
so these claims
are worthless these claims are all false
they're all lies we have
still even today
millions of records of ancient
documentation which nobody has even
looked into
who knows how old these records are some
of them could be thousands of years old
possibly
potentially
we will know only when these records are
dis
are
deciphered they're analyzed and their
carbon dating or whatever is done then
we know
so why is all of this not being done and
that is the reason why all of these
misconceptions
continue until today
okay
pushpedra says are there infinitely many
prime numbers yes there are infinitely
many prime numbers and this can be
proven using school level mathematics i
will not prove it here because i don't
have a whiteboard or whatever but it can
be proven that there are infinitely many
prime numbers using school level
mathematics there are multiple there are
a multitude of ways of proving this but
you can do it with school level
mathematics as well
so the answer is yes there are
infinitely many
prime
numbers
pratishwar says you have educated us on
the topic of power and leadership a few
times now
can you please expand further on this
topic
people say money is power but is money
really power
if a person
has more money does it mean he or she is
more powerful can a person with decent
money become powerful
these are interesting questions right
is a good amount of money a must
for a person to become
powerful
basically what is the
oh sorry
basically what's the real difference in
relation between power and money which
people misunderstand quite a lot
so
this is a complicated topic
power is completely different from money
money is currency money is something
that represents a certain kind of value
which can be used to acquire materials
goods services even power
so you may have a lot of money it
doesn't mean that you have power power
is different power means
power means the cooperation of people
not just cooperation obedience of people
it is that obedience of people that
creates
power
look at any dictator king emperor queen
whatever in the world politician of
today
where does that power come from it comes
from
the fact that people will obey them and
do what what what is being told that is
where power comes from so you can buy
power if you already have some power you
can buy more power with money
there are certain rules
in power
certain secrets
are
so imagine that you are
let's say hypothetically a saddam
hussein kind of dictator
you have a country that you are a
dictator of
how do you maximize your power
you have to depend on other people for
power whether it is
whether it is kim jong-un whether it is
xi jinping whether it was julius caesar
whether it was alexander the tyrant
whoever these powerful people were their
power they had no power without the
obedience of other people
so how do you acquire more power there
are certain
secrets
let me go into a couple of these secrets
first secret
is
must depend on as few possible as few
people
as possible
if you want to maximize your power
you will need a certain number of
indispensable people who will be your
enforcers who will do the things you
need them to do for instance mohandas
gandhi had an enforcer his name was
wallaby patel
patel was the enforcer of gandhi the guy
who did all the organizational
activities and kept the congress party
minions in line
he was the enforcer he was the iron
disciplined man
he did the organization on all those
activities so mohandas gandhi depended
on wallop by patel for this enforcement
in
organizational activity
so one guy was enough for gandhi he did
not need 15 people to do that only one
guy was enough and patel would have a
number of his own
chosen few people who would do the work
for the for him that's how it works it's
an organizational hierarchy so the first
rule of power is you must depend on as
few people as possible the indispensable
people
but
the number of the group of people you
can really trust make it as large as
possible
that is the second rule of power right
and there are other things as well so
all of this has nothing to do with money
it has to do
with how you deal with people and how
you organize your power structure
now the second point that i spoke about
that depend on
the the group that you are that is loyal
to you the group that the people you can
trust make it as large as possible in
that money can come in
you can buy loyalty and obedience with
money in that big group but the small
group
you cannot buy with money for that you
need a certain shared ideology or shared
purpose
it's a complicated thing i am just
skimming the surface of how it is
so that's how power works that's how
politics works
you'll understand if you get deep into
it someday
so that's what i can say all right that
brings me to the end of today's session
it's almost two hours thank you very
much for all the questions i have so
many other questions that i've not taken
up hopefully we'll keep doing this and i
will take some more questions next time
but for today this is the end of today's
session thank you very much everybody
for your questions for your viewership
your support
and we will keep doing this i will see
you
in next week's session thank you take
care good night good day bye